export const jambCommerce = [
  {
    question: "Compulsory dissolution of a business can arise from _____",
    options: [
      "a declaration by a court",
      "an agreement by the owners",
      "an unfavourable economic climate",
      "the termination of its life",
    ],
    answer: "a declaration by a court",
  },
  {
    question: "A proforma invoice is not required when _____",
    options: [
      "goods are sent on approval",
      "quoting for the supply of goods",
      "final prices are uncertain",
      "dealing regularly with a customer",
    ],
    answer: "goods are sent on approval",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Given: ₦ Opening stock 40,000 Purchases 115,000 Closing stock 60,000 Sales 250,000 What is the cost of goods sold?",
    options: ["₦50,000", "₦30,000", "₦95,000", "₦155,000"],
    answer: "₦95,000",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In the channel of distribution, which of the following sets is entirely made up of middlemen?",
    options: [
      "Manufacturers, consumers and retailers",
      "Wholesalers, retailers and agents",
      "Retailers, manufacturers, and wholesalers",
      "Wholesalers, agents and consumers",
    ],
    answer: "Wholesalers, retailers and agents",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The conversion of raw materials into finished product creates _____",
    options: [
      "form utility",
      "marginal utility",
      "time utility",
      "place utility",
    ],
    answer: "form utility",
  },
  {
    question: "Commerce makes it possible for man to live in a _____",
    options: [
      "complex and organized society",
      "simple and organized society",
      "society characterized by subsistency",
      "society characterized by dependency",
    ],
    answer: "complex and organized society",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The insurance principle that requires full disclosure of information on the insured is known as _____",
    options: ["caveat empto", "subrogation", "uberrimae fidei", "indemnity"],
    answer: "uberrimae fidei",
  },
  {
    question: "Production involves _____",
    options: [
      "changing the form of goods, moulding and making, them available as needed",
      "making goods available when and where needed",
      "the assembling of all necessary parts to produce",
      "the manufacturing of goods and provision of services",
    ],
    answer: "the manufacturing of goods and provision of services",
  },
  {
    question: "A merchant wholesaler is referred to as _____",
    options: ["a factor", "rack gobber", "a broker", "del-credere agent"],
    answer: "a factor",
  },
  {
    question: "A proforma invoice is sent to inform a buyer about the _____",
    options: [
      "prices of goods",
      "quantity of goods",
      "quality of goods",
      "designation of goods",
    ],
    answer: "prices of goods",
  },
  {
    question: "Capital as a factor of production can be used for _____",
    options: [
      "goods that are useful in business",
      "money that is regarded as assets",
      "services that provide satisfaction",
      "input for further production",
    ],
    answer: "input for further production",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The agency that currently oversees the privatization and commercialization processes in Nigeria is the _____",
    options: [
      "Bureau of public enterprises",
      "Nigerian stock exchange",
      "Technical committee on privatization and commercialization",
      "Securities and Exchange Commission",
    ],
    answer: "Bureau of public enterprises",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The payment made periodically in respect of an insurance policy entered into is known as _____",
    options: ["premium", "surrender", "bond", "commission"],
    answer: "premium",
  },
  {
    question: "An example of services rendered by NIPOST is _____",
    options: ["courier", "electronic mail", "mail delivery", "Telephone"],
    answer: "mail delivery",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Ships that sail across the ocean and operate on scheduled timetables are _____",
    options: ["coastal liners", "tramp steamer", "ocean liners", "ferries"],
    answer: "ocean liners",
  },
  {
    question: "Non-insurable risks include _____",
    options: ["death", "marine problems", "damage to property", "gambling"],
    answer: "gambling",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The most important right of the employee in discharging his duties to the employer is the right to _____",
    options: [
      "job securities",
      "annual leave",
      "regular enrolments",
      "working facilities",
    ],
    answer: "job securities",
  },
  {
    question: "The most dangerous pollution is _____",
    options: [
      "Air pollution",
      "water pollution",
      "Soil pollution",
      "noise pollution",
    ],
    answer: "Air pollution",
  },
  {
    question: "Tourism can be classified as _____",
    options: [
      "visible exports",
      "invisible exports",
      "tangible imports",
      "intangible imports",
    ],
    answer: "invisible exports",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The inputs, output, and central processing units are the basic components of a _____",
    options: ["software", "hardware", "memory", "printer"],
    answer: "hardware",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Consumers require protection against exploitation to ensure _____",
    options: [
      "the sale of quality products",
      "increased aggregate demand",
      "adequate consumer awareness",
      "availability of product variety",
    ],
    answer: "the sale of quality products",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The business environment that takes into cognizance the age distribution, ethnic mix, and educational level of consumers is _____",
    options: [
      "cultural environment",
      "national environment",
      "demographic environment",
      "economic environment",
    ],
    answer: "demographic environment",
  },
  {
    question:
      "An activity that involves derivation of raw materials from land and sea is _____",
    options: ["agricultural", "extraction", "construction", "farming"],
    answer: "extraction",
  },
  {
    question: "The art of soap-making is an example of _____",
    options: [
      "secondary occupation",
      "primary occupation",
      "construction occupation",
      "tertiary occupation",
    ],
    answer: "secondary occupation",
  },
  {
    question: "The central focus of commercial activities is _____",
    options: ["pricing", "marketing", "advertising", "farming"],
    answer: "marketing",
  },
  {
    question: "An aid to trade associated with communication is _____",
    options: ["insurance", "warehousing", "banking", "transportation"],
    answer: "banking",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following can be used to differentiate skilled and unskilled labour?",
    options: [
      "Available resources",
      "Education and training",
      "Salaries and wages",
      "Level of commitment",
    ],
    answer: "Education and training",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A doctor who attends to patients at home after his official duty is _____",
    options: [
      "a direct and indirect service worker",
      "an indirect service worker",
      "a direct service worker",
      "a community developer",
    ],
    answer: "a direct service worker",
  },
  {
    question: "An oil exploration company is engaged in _____",
    options: [
      "extractive occupation",
      "constructive occupation",
      "secondary production",
      "tertiary production",
    ],
    answer: "extractive occupation",
  },
  {
    question: "Services rendered to the public are provided by _____",
    options: [
      "governments",
      "domestic servants",
      "professionals",
      "civil servants",
    ],
    answer: "governments",
  },
  {
    question:
      "If a customer pays within nine days of receiving goods and takes advantage of 3% off the invoice price, this is stated as _____",
    options: ["30; net 9/3", "9/30; net 3", "9/27 net 30", "3/9; net 30"],
    answer: "3/9; net 30",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a characteristic of a bearer cheque?",
    options: [
      "it is made payable to whoever presents it",
      "it is made with transverse lines",
      "it is only payable into the payee's account",
      "it is made without transverse",
    ],
    answer: "it is made payable to whoever presents it",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A country is said to be experiencing an unfavourable balance of trade if her _____",
    options: [
      "exports exceed imports.",
      "visible exports exceed visible imports.",
      "imports and exports are equal.",
      "visible imports exceed visible exports.",
    ],
    answer: "visible imports exceed visible exports.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The type of labour that makes use of physical efforts in production procession is the _____",
    options: [
      "skilled labour",
      "unskilled labour",
      "white-collar job",
      "blue-collar job",
    ],
    answer: "unskilled labour",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the main objective of setting up a public corporation?",
    options: [
      "To provide free goods and services",
      "To satisfy the profit motive",
      "To enable the government earn foreign revenue",
      "To serve the public interest",
    ],
    answer: "To serve the public interest",
  },
  {
    question: "A business with a profit motive is often referred to as a _____",
    options: [
      "free enterprise",
      "public enterprise",
      "private enterprise",
      "co-operative enterprise",
    ],
    answer: "private enterprise",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is an advantage of a sole proprietorship?",
    options: [
      "Unlimited liability",
      "Limited capital",
      "Greater control",
      "Limited workload",
    ],
    answer: "Greater control",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The process whereby the federal government entrusts some of its duties and obligations to state governments is called _____",
    options: ["cooperation", "delegation", "privatization", "devolution"],
    answer: "devolution",
  },
  {
    question: "A condition for setting up a business is _____",
    options: ["good location", "good government", "capital", "workers"],
    answer: "capital",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following describes the act of reducing workload by assigning duties to junior workers?",
    options: ["Employment", "Entrustment", "Delegation", "Promotion"],
    answer: "Delegation",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the main advantage of using air transport?",
    options: [
      "Cheap for carrying bulky goods",
      "Carries goods to faraway places",
      "Suitable for heavy products",
      "Quick delivery over long distances",
    ],
    answer: "Quick delivery over long distances",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The shipping document that shows ownership of goods is the _____",
    options: ["bill of entry", "manifest", "ship manifest", "bill of lading"],
    answer: "bill of lading",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The agency that guarantees the quality of goods sold in Nigeria is the _____",
    options: [
      "Standard Organisation of Nigeria (SON)",
      "Nigeria Customs Service",
      "Nigerian Ports Authority",
      "Nigerian Export Promotion Council",
    ],
    answer: "Standard Organisation of Nigeria (SON)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The rate where a country's exports exchange for its imports is called _____",
    options: [
      "terms of payments",
      "terms of trade",
      "balance of payments",
      "balance of trade",
    ],
    answer: "terms of trade",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The use of coin-operated machines to sell goods is a form of _____",
    options: [
      "mail-order selling",
      "personal selling",
      "retailer",
      "wholesaling",
    ],
    answer: "retailer",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The insurance policy which provides full cover against all risks at sea is known as _____",
    options: [
      "marine voyage policy insurance",
      "marine freight insurance",
      "policy free of particular average",
      "policy with particular average",
    ],
    answer: "policy free of particular average",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The practice by which an insurance company accepts a very large risk and later shares it with other insurance companies is called _____",
    options: ["contribution", "indemnity", "subrogation", "re-insurance"],
    answer: "re-insurance",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A machine that enables sales without the physical presence of a sales attendant is a _____",
    options: [
      "vending machine",
      "computer machine",
      "fax machine",
      "telex machine",
    ],
    answer: "vending machine",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What document is required when a country imposes ad valorem import duties on goods?",
    options: [
      "Consular invoice",
      "A bill of lading",
      "A shipping note",
      "A mail transfer",
    ],
    answer: "Consular invoice",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A business whose owners enjoy loan facilities based on personal goodwill is a _____",
    options: [
      "community bank",
      "co-operative society",
      "commercial bank",
      "thrifts society",
    ],
    answer: "co-operative society",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is not a veritable source of funds to a public limited liability company?",
    options: [
      "advances and loans from banks",
      "government financial grants",
      "funds from the sale of shares",
      "internally generated funds",
    ],
    answer: "government financial grants",
  },
  {
    question: "The term PLC implies that the shares are available _____",
    options: [
      "publicly on the stock exchange",
      "publicly in commercial bank",
      "privately on the stock exchange",
      "to the public at the company",
    ],
    answer: "publicly on the stock exchange",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of these is both a merit and demerit in partnership?",
    options: [
      "Its unlimited nature",
      "The number of partners",
      "The withdrawal of a major partner",
      "The bearing of risk",
    ],
    answer: "The withdrawal of a major partner",
  },
  {
    question: "A factor necessary for siting a warehouse is nearness to _____",
    options: ["labour", "capital", "consumers", "raw materials"],
    answer: "consumers",
  },
  {
    question: "Pooling of risk in insurance means that _____",
    options: [
      "two people can pool their risks to be insured",
      "compensations are paid out of a common fund",
      "insurance companies should encourage taking risks",
      "two insurance companies can buy two policies",
    ],
    answer: "compensations are paid out of a common fund",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following countries are members of the Lake Chad Basin Commission?",
    options: [
      "Benin and Nigeria",
      "Nigeria and Mali",
      "Niger and Cameroun",
      "Chad and Benin",
    ],
    answer: "Niger and Cameroun",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A core investor in the current phase of privatization in Nigeria is one who _____",
    options: [
      "has the technical know-how of the enterprises",
      "can mobilize foreign currency equivalent to the value of enterprises",
      "will be at the core of the enterprises",
      "can afford to buy most of the shares of the enterprises",
    ],
    answer: "can afford to buy most of the shares of the enterprises",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The process of dividing tasks into jobs and departments and delegating authority is known as _____",
    options: ["organizing", "staffing", "leading", "directing"],
    answer: "organizing",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The communication process involves the transmission of a message over a selected channel to the _____",
    options: ["encoder", "receiver", "audience", "sender"],
    answer: "receiver",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A transporter who had to sell perishable goods without the prior authority of the owner becomes an agent by _____",
    options: ["estoppel", "conduct", "necessity", "ratification"],
    answer: "necessity",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Poor sewage disposal, oil spills, and indiscriminate refuse dumping all lead to _____",
    options: [
      "land and water pollution",
      "air and water pollution",
      "land pollution",
      "water pollution",
    ],
    answer: "land and water pollution",
  },
  {
    question: "A major function of a Chamber of Commerce is _____",
    options: [
      "promoting both home and foreign trade",
      "increasing productivity",
      "maximizing profit",
      "promoting trade in a particular area",
    ],
    answer: "promoting both home and foreign trade",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the middlemen in the channel of distribution has title to the goods he distributes?",
    options: [
      "The retailer",
      "The limited wholesaler",
      "The agents",
      "The merchant wholesaler",
    ],
    answer: "The merchant wholesaler",
  },
  {
    question: "A seller attracts and retains patronage by _____",
    options: [
      "rendering pre-sales services",
      "enhancing sales promotion",
      "rendering customer service",
      "enhancing public relations",
    ],
    answer: "rendering pre-sales services",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A bond that attracts only interest but leaves the capital unpaid is referred to as _____",
    options: [
      "a redeemable bond",
      "an irredeemable bond",
      "a long-term loan",
      "a development bond",
    ],
    answer: "an irredeemable bond",
  },
  {
    question:
      "An announcement of a person's willingness to enter into a contract is referred to as _____",
    options: ["consideration", "an acceptance", "a proxy", "an offer"],
    answer: "an offer",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The macro-environmental forces and trends that are a constraint on business operations are referred to as _____",
    options: [
      "external factors",
      "internal factors",
      "economic factors",
      "technological factors",
    ],
    answer: "external factors",
  },
  {
    question: "A proposed company may not be registered if _____",
    options: [
      "it has no paid-up capital",
      "it has no asset of its own",
      "it does not put 'limited' after its proposed name",
      "the name conflicts with that of another",
    ],
    answer: "the name conflicts with that of another",
  },
  {
    question: "An example of a cartel is _____",
    options: ["EU", "AU", "OPEC", "ECOWAS"],
    answer: "OPEC",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which of the following will the number of words used determine the cost of a message sent?",
    options: ["E-mail", "Telex", "Telegram", "Telephone"],
    answer: "Telegram",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The transmission of telephone services from one country to another is facilitated by _____",
    options: [
      "international facility",
      "communication satellite",
      "internet services",
      "interconnectivity",
    ],
    answer: "communication satellite",
  },
  {
    question: "After-sales service is a function usually rendered by _____",
    options: ["an entrepreneur", "an agent", "wholesale", "a retailer"],
    answer: "a retailer",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The activity that entails buying goods in bulk and selling in small quantities to retailers is _____",
    options: ["wholesaling", "assembling", "retailing", "merchandising"],
    answer: "wholesaling",
  },
  {
    question:
      "An individual that links the producer with the retailer is _____",
    options: ["a principal", "an agent", "an entrepreneur", "a wholesaler"],
    answer: "a wholesaler",
  },
  {
    question: "One of the functions of a retailer is _____",
    options: [
      "breaking of bulk",
      "financing of production activities",
      "provision of credit facilities to relations",
      "provision of jobs for customers",
    ],
    answer: "breaking of bulk",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The type of letters delivered through normal mail or by airmail express service is referred to as _____",
    options: [
      "airmail letters",
      "inland letters",
      "registered letters",
      "express letters",
    ],
    answer: "express letters",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A business organization that exploits the capabilities of a member to remedy the weaknesses of another is a _____",
    options: [
      "co-operative",
      "joint venture",
      "partnership",
      "nominal partnership",
    ],
    answer: "partnership",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following regulates and controls the activities in the Nigeria Stock Exchange?",
    options: ["SEC", "BPE", "CBN", "NDIC"],
    answer: "SEC",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The payment made by a speculator to the buyer when he is unable to deliver stocks on the agreed date is _____",
    options: ["backwardation", "Franco", "arbitrage", "contango"],
    answer: "backwardation",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Part payments made on allotted shares by subscribers is usually the _____",
    options: [
      "issued capital",
      "subscribed capital",
      "called-up capital",
      "authorized capital",
    ],
    answer: "called-up capital",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A loan to a customer with a cheque account at a bank in which the account is allowed to go into debit is _____",
    options: ["advance", "over draft", "commission", "interest"],
    answer: "over draft",
  },
  {
    question: "Money is generally acceptable for transaction due to _____",
    options: [
      "the rule of the law",
      "its acceptability in the global market",
      "the legal backing",
      "the Central Bank Governor's signature",
    ],
    answer: "the legal backing",
  },
  {
    question: "Trade fairs in Nigeria are organized by _____",
    options: [
      "Ministry of commerce and industry",
      "chambers of commerce",
      "The federal Government",
      "Manufacturer's Association of Nigeria",
    ],
    answer: "chambers of commerce",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Goods and services are made available to consumers through _____",
    options: [
      "the advertising agency",
      "sales promotion",
      "the channel of distribution",
      "the middle men",
    ],
    answer: "the channel of distribution",
  },
  {
    question:
      "An organization which focuses on consumer satisfaction is practising _____",
    options: [
      "marketing concept",
      "selling concept",
      "consumerism",
      "market segmentation",
    ],
    answer: "marketing concept",
  },
  {
    question:
      "One of the major disadvantages of pipeline transportation is its _____",
    options: [
      "high maintenance cost",
      "high cost of construction",
      "Limitation in scope",
      "vulnerability to climate changes",
    ],
    answer: "Limitation in scope",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The business organization that can effectively combine management with control is ____",
    options: [
      "co-operative society",
      "public limited liability company",
      "private limited liability company",
      "sole proprietorship",
    ],
    answer: "sole proprietorship",
  },
  {
    question:
      "An arrangement by independent firms to share the market of their products on quota basis is referred to as _____",
    options: ["cartel", "syndicate", "trust", "integration"],
    answer: "cartel",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The warehouse that is owned and controlled by the government is a _____",
    options: [
      "state warehouse",
      "wholesalers' warehouse",
      "public warehouse",
      "manufacturers' warehouse",
    ],
    answer: "public warehouse",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In a public limited liability company, planning is carried out by _____",
    options: [
      "employees",
      "the chairman of the board",
      "shareholders",
      "manufacturers' warehouse",
    ],
    answer: "the chairman of the board",
  },
  {
    question:
      "One of the major problems of a sole proprietor is sourcing for _____",
    options: ["funds", "labour", "raw materials", "machineries"],
    answer: "funds",
  },
  {
    question: "Balance of payments is made up of _____",
    options: [
      "currency and capital items",
      "visible and current items",
      "visible and invisible items",
      "visible and capital items",
    ],
    answer: "visible and invisible items",
  },
  {
    question: "The four P's of marketing are _____",
    options: [
      "Price, product, property and place",
      "Product, place, process and promotion",
      "Price, production, place and property",
      "Price, product, place and promotion",
    ],
    answer: "Price, product, place and promotion",
  },
  {
    question: "The inter for is a system of telecommunications used for ____",
    options: [
      "sending electronic messages",
      "communicating long-distance messages",
      "sending and receiving text messages",
      "communicating messages through telegrams",
    ],
    answer: "sending and receiving text messages",
  },
  {
    question: "The major determinant of fire insurance premium is the _____",
    options: [
      "usefulness of the property to the owner",
      "type and structure of the property to be insured",
      "extent of fixed damage anticipated",
      "owner of the property to be insured",
    ],
    answer: "type and structure of the property to be insured",
  },
  {
    question: "Capital to a business is technically _____",
    options: ["an asset", "a project", "a liability", "an expense"],
    answer: "an asset",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The factor which critically determines the choice of occupation is _____",
    options: ["skill", "training", "aptitude", "interest"],
    answer: "interest",
  },
  {
    question:
      "From which of the following sources can partnerships increase their capital?",
    options: [
      "Sales of shares",
      "Admission of new partners",
      "Discharge of mortgage",
      "Grants from relations",
    ],
    answer: "Admission of new partners",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In Nigeria, the ministry in charge of registering trade associations is that of _____",
    options: ["culture and tourism", "finance", "industries", "commerce"],
    answer: "commerce",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The shares of a company listed on the stock exchange for sale are referred to as _____",
    options: [
      "quoted shares",
      "issue shares",
      "deferred shares",
      "registered shares",
    ],
    answer: "quoted shares",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Charges for loans paid by commercial banks to the central bank of Nigeria are called _____",
    options: ["Credit charges", "bank rates", "bank charges", "interest rates"],
    answer: "bank rates",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The act of a person employing another to enter into a contract on his behalf is known as _____",
    options: ["agency", "bilateral agreement", "business", "sale of goods"],
    answer: "agency",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Social responsibility is the ability of an organization to _____",
    options: [
      "operate without disrupting the very essence of the environment",
      "tackle the socio-economic problems of its community",
      "meet the needs of its community",
      "contribute to sustaining and developing its community",
    ],
    answer: "contribute to sustaining and developing its community",
  },
  {
    question:
      "An author's exclusive right to his published and unpublished works is known as _____",
    options: [
      "constitutional right",
      "copy right",
      "author right",
      "patent right",
    ],
    answer: "copy right",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Awarding scholarships and sponsoring sports by a business organization are examples of _____",
    options: [
      "social responsibility",
      "advertising strategy",
      "marketing strategy",
      "economic responsibility",
    ],
    answer: "social responsibility",
  },
  {
    question:
      "One way by which government reduces the repatriation of capital is through _____",
    options: [
      "divestiture",
      "naturalization",
      "nationalization",
      "indigenization",
    ],
    answer: "indigenization",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The maximum number of shareholders in a public liability company is _____",
    options: ["one hundred", "unlimited", "fifty", "twenty"],
    answer: "unlimited",
  },
  {
    question: "Bank overdraft as a short term source of fund is _____",
    options: [
      "a current liability",
      "an overdrawn account",
      "grade to a newly opened account",
      "repayable after more than a year",
    ],
    answer: "a current liability",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A company which issues a promissory note in lieu of payment for goods purchased _____",
    options: [
      "is not bound to renew the note before payment",
      "can return the goods purchased and refuse to pay",
      "can refuse to pay on due date since it is only a promise",
      "is bound to redeem the note for cash on due date",
    ],
    answer: "is bound to redeem the note for cash on due date",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Insurance companies operate on the principle of indemnity. This means that an insured person or firm collects _____",
    options: [
      "double the value of loss suffered",
      "only half of the loss suffered",
      "the total sum of the premiums paid prior to the loss",
      "compensation equal to the loss suffered",
    ],
    answer: "compensation equal to the loss suffered",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The two main categories under which marine losses fall are _____",
    options: [
      "total loss and partial loss",
      "voyage policy loss and time policy loss",
      "particular loss and average loss",
      "actual loss and general loss",
    ],
    answer: "total loss and partial loss",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Chinyere agreed to supply Adamu 20 cartons of provision in two weeks time. This type of contract is _____",
    options: ["implied", "executed", "express", "executory"],
    answer: "executory",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When demand for a commodity changes with changes in its price, the demand is _____",
    options: ["elastic", "increasing", "inversely related", "unitary elastic"],
    answer: "elastic",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Insurance premium paid on goods bought on CIF basis is borne by the _____",
    options: ["importer", "exporter", "shipping company", "insurance company"],
    answer: "exporter",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following factors is essential in selecting a good office machine?",
    options: [
      "Weight of the machine",
      "Distance of the machine to the work area",
      "Cost of servicing the machine",
      "availability of supply of spare parts",
    ],
    answer: "availability of supply of spare parts",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The institution set up to encourage small businesses in Nigeria is the _____",
    options: [
      "people's bank",
      "Federal mortgage bank",
      "Nigeria Bank for commerce and industry",
      "Community Bank",
    ],
    answer: "Nigeria Bank for commerce and industry",
  },
  {
    question: "NACCIMA stands for _____",
    options: [
      "Nigerian-American Centre for Culture, Industries, Mines and Arts",
      "Nigerian Association of Chambers of Commerce, Industries, Mines and Agriculture",
      "Nigerian Association for Culture, Civics, Industries, Minerals and Arts",
      "National Agency for Culture, Civilization, Investments, Manufacturing and Agriculture",
    ],
    answer:
      "Nigerian Association of Chambers of Commerce, Industries, Mines and Agriculture",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Motivation is an essential element in management because it _____",
    options: [
      "helps to eliminate industrial disharmony",
      "leads to the improvement of staff welfare",
      "encourages individuals to work towards achieving the organization's objectives",
      "reduces friction among employees in the process of achieving the organization's objectives",
    ],
    answer:
      "encourages individuals to work towards achieving the organization's objectives",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The direct authority of a superior over his subordinate is known as _____",
    options: [
      "line authority",
      "line and staff authority",
      "staff authority",
      "lane authority",
    ],
    answer: "line authority",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A minor is not permitted to enter into a valid contract because he _____",
    options: [
      "is young in the eye of the law",
      "may not be able to write the contract",
      "cannot pay the consideration",
      "is too young to interpret the law",
    ],
    answer: "is young in the eye of the law",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A person who is cheated in a business transaction can seek legal remedy _____",
    options: [
      "regardless of the form of business organization",
      "only if the transaction is documented in a contract",
      "even if the agreement is verbal and the amount involved is large",
      "only if the business is a sole proprietorship whose owner is known",
    ],
    answer: "even if the agreement is verbal and the amount involved is large",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following documents permits an importer to inspect his goods before the arrival of the bill of lading?",
    options: [
      "Import invoice",
      "Bill of exchange",
      "Bill of sight",
      "Consular invoice",
    ],
    answer: "Bill of sight",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The overriding advantage of home trade over foreign trade is _____",
    options: [
      "ease in language of transaction",
      "absence of many documents",
      "accessibility of seller to buyer",
      "ease in form of payment",
    ],
    answer: "accessibility of seller to buyer",
  },
  {
    question: "The function of a merchant wholesaler is to _____",
    options: [
      "find markets for producers' finished goods",
      "bring buyers and sellers together",
      "buy in bulk, store and sell to retailers as desired",
      "possess title to the goods, store and sell to retailers",
    ],
    answer: "buy in bulk, store and sell to retailers as desired",
  },
  {
    question: "An invoice can be described as a _____",
    options: [
      "document specifying quantity, description, prices and total value of purchases",
      "receipt containing necessary information about the goods",
      "letter specifying the contractual sales of goods between two parties",
      "contractual agreement for the sale of goods",
    ],
    answer:
      "document specifying quantity, description, prices and total value of purchases",
  },
  {
    question: "Departmentalization is an aspect of _____",
    options: ["directing", "controlling", "organizing", "planning"],
    answer: "organizing",
  },
  {
    question: "A functional organizational structure is where _____",
    options: [
      "activities of similar nature are grouped together",
      "staff performing the same functions are grouped together",
      "departments performing similar functions are grouped together",
      "staff performing similar functions are grouped together",
    ],
    answer: "activities of similar nature are grouped together",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The mode of transporting crude oil to the ports for export purposes is by _____",
    options: ["road", "pipeline", "tanker", "rail"],
    answer: "pipeline",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The temporary insurance certificate issued to the insured before drawing up a policy is a _____",
    options: ["testimonial", "cover note", "time policy", "proposal form"],
    answer: "cover note",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A type of long-term loan granted to companies with fixed interest as well as with redeemable and irredeemable features is referred to as _____",
    options: ["an overdraft", "a term loan", "a debenture", "a bond"],
    answer: "a debenture",
  },
  {
    question: "Public debt management is one of the functions of a _____",
    options: [
      "Development bank",
      "Merchant bank",
      "Central bank",
      "Commercial bank",
    ],
    answer: "Central bank",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The strategy adopted by a firm that ceases to operate at one or more locations because of inactivity is _____",
    options: ["focus", "diversification", "rejuvenation", "consolidation"],
    answer: "consolidation",
  },
  {
    question: "A written partnership contract is known as _____",
    options: ["a deed", "an invoice", "a proposal", "a prospectus"],
    answer: "a deed",
  },
  {
    question:
      "To increase the supply of money in a country, the central bank has to _____",
    options: [
      "call on special deposits",
      "raise cash ratio",
      "lower the cash ratio",
      "sell securities in the open market",
    ],
    answer: "lower the cash ratio",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A good financial instrument which serves as a hedge against inflation is _____",
    options: ["a warrant", "a bond", "a share", "an option"],
    answer: "a bond",
  },
  {
    question: "The major types of warehouses are _____",
    options: [
      "bonded, public, cold room and private",
      "manufacturer, bonded, departmental and private",
      "wholesaler, manufacturer, public and bonded",
      "manufacturer, bonded, public and departmental",
    ],
    answer: "bonded, public, cold room and private",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The Customs and Excise Department is responsible for the collection of _____",
    options: ["royalties", "taxes", "tariffs", "charges"],
    answer: "tariffs",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following requires payment into the payee's account?",
    options: [
      "Certified cheque",
      "Traveller's cheque",
      "Crossed cheque",
      "Open cheque",
    ],
    answer: "Crossed cheque",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The traditional way of paying cooperative dividend is to distribute profit in proportion to members' _____",
    options: [
      "contributions",
      "total savings",
      "subscriptions",
      "volume of purchases",
    ],
    answer: "contributions",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The practice whereby government relinquishes its ownership interest in a public enterprise is _____",
    options: [
      "nationalization",
      "privatization",
      "commercialization",
      "indigenization",
    ],
    answer: "privatization",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A factor in a business environment which increases the rate of product obsolescence is _____",
    options: ["political", "legal", "technology", "economic"],
    answer: "technology",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A customer with XYZ Plc sent money through his account to his sister's account in another branch. This is an example of _____",
    options: ["e-business", "e-banking", "e-commerce", "e-finance"],
    answer: "e-banking",
  },
  {
    question: "The economic environment of a business is concerned with _____",
    options: [
      "changing values",
      "the interest rate",
      "climatic conditions",
      "the growth rate",
    ],
    answer: "the interest rate",
  },
  {
    question: "In e-banking, ATM means _____",
    options: [
      "Authentic Teller Machine",
      "All-purpose Teller Machine",
      "Automatic Teller Machine",
      "Automated Teller Machine",
    ],
    answer: "Automated Teller Machine",
  },
  {
    question:
      "One way by which a business can discharge its social responsibility to its community is to _____",
    options: [
      "award scholarship to staff children",
      "build public health centres",
      "contribute to international organizations",
      "contribute towards pollution of the environment",
    ],
    answer: "build public health centres",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following represents a form of business combination?",
    options: ["consortium", "patent", "merger", "copyright"],
    answer: "merger",
  },
  {
    question: "The clearing house in banking is owned by _____",
    options: [
      "the commercial banks",
      "the clearing banks",
      "the central bank",
      "the merchant bank",
    ],
    answer: "the central bank",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Social responsibility of business means that a business should _____",
    options: [
      "maximize profit",
      "increase the number of employees",
      "provide employment for local citizens",
      "contribute to the social goals of the community",
    ],
    answer: "contribute to the social goals of the community",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A distinguishing characteristic of a limited liability company is that it _____",
    options: [
      "is a collection of many sole proprietors",
      "is a multiple partnership",
      "has limited resources",
      "can sue and be sued",
    ],
    answer: "can sue and be sued",
  },
  {
    question: "Freight note is a document _____",
    options: [
      "issued by a shipping company giving details of charges",
      "used by government to transport goods from one country to another",
      "used for payment for imported goods",
      "given by an importer to pay for goods at a future period",
    ],
    answer: "issued by a shipping company giving details of charges",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following are the components of commerce?",
    options: [
      "trading and advertising",
      "warehousing and transportation",
      "packing and branding",
      "Insurance and banking",
    ],
    answer: "I, II and IV",
  },
  {
    question: "Extractive industries may also be denominated as _____",
    options: [
      "direct industries",
      "servicing industries",
      "indirect industries",
      "primary industries",
    ],
    answer: "primary industries",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A common requirement for public and private limited companies in Nigeria is that ____",
    options: [
      "a shareholder cannot transfer his shares to someone else without permission from other shareholders",
      "shares cannot be offered for sale on the stock exchange",
      "their annual accounts are made available to the corporate affairs commission",
      "shares can be offered for sale through an issuing house",
    ],
    answer:
      "a shareholder cannot transfer his shares to someone else without permission from other shareholders",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Mr. Olatunde took up a fire insurance on a property valued at ₦1000 and the amount insured is ₦80. The property caught fire causing a loss of ₦400. If the insurance was taken with the clause 'with average', what is the amount to be paid by the insurance company?",
    options: ["₦420", "₦320", "₦460", "₦560"],
    answer: "₦320",
  },
  {
    question:
      "One major characteristic of credit unions and thrift societies is that _____",
    options: [
      "the contribution of every member depends on the member's ability",
      "the legal processes involved in their formation are rigid",
      "membership is compulsory to people in the same line of business",
      "a minimum of ten people in the same line of business can form the union",
    ],
    answer: "the contribution of every member depends on the member's ability",
  },
  {
    question:
      "An author's exclusive right to his published and unpublished works is known as _____",
    options: [
      "constitutional right",
      "author's right",
      "copyright",
      "patent right",
    ],
    answer: "copyright",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The management function that makes the difference in intensity of behavior is _____",
    options: ["controlling", "motivation", "coordinating", "planning"],
    answer: "motivation",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Charges for loans paid by commercial banks to the Central Bank of Nigeria are called _____",
    options: ["credit charges", "interest rates", "bank charges", "bank rates"],
    answer: "interest rates",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The difference between personal selling and sales promotion is that while sales promotion includes free gifts and samples, personal selling involves _____",
    options: [
      "face-to-face communication with customers",
      "distributing instructional posters",
      "premium programming for customers",
      "publishing promotional booklets",
    ],
    answer: "face-to-face communication with customers",
  },
  {
    question: "One of the disadvantages of sole proprietorship is _____",
    options: [
      "limited liability",
      "pride of ownership",
      "unlimited liability",
      "secrecy of annual reports",
    ],
    answer: "unlimited liability",
  },
  {
    question:
      "One of the functions of the Nigeria Ports Authority is the provision of _____",
    options: [
      "carrier services to ensure speedy delivery",
      "facilities to enhance the speedy loading and offloading of cargoes",
      "facilities to ensure that goods get to the destinations",
      "shelter for operators of cargoes",
    ],
    answer:
      "facilities to enhance the speedy loading and offloading of cargoes",
  },
  {
    question: "The scope of economic activities can be enlarged by ____",
    options: [
      "transportation and trading",
      "trading and aids to trade",
      "business and its promotion",
      "insurance and banking",
    ],
    answer: "trading and aids to trade",
  },
  {
    question: "Ships used for international transport are _____",
    options: ["oceanliners", "yachts", "launchers", "trawlers"],
    answer: "oceanliners",
  },
  {
    question: "The process of eliminating a virus from a computer is the ____",
    options: ["programming", "formatting", "looping", "debugging"],
    answer: "debugging",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A customer with ABC Plc sent money through his account to his sister's account in another branch. This is an example of _____",
    options: ["e-business", "e-commerce", "e-banking", "e-finance"],
    answer: "e-banking",
  },
  {
    question:
      "One of the merits of television as a medium of advertising is that it _____",
    options: [
      "is prone to censorship",
      "is relatively cheap",
      "has more network coverage",
      "has more sensory stimulation",
    ],
    answer: "has more sensory stimulation",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The central working system of a computer used for data processing in the _____",
    options: ["monitor", "floppy disk drive", "hard drive", "memory unit"],
    answer: "hard drive",
  },
  {
    question: "An example of a computer operating system is _____",
    options: [
      "the PageMaker",
      "Windows 2000",
      "Microsoft Word 2000",
      "The Word Perfect",
    ],
    answer: "Windows 2000",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The arrangement and interrelationship of the various components and positions of a business is referred to as _____",
    options: [
      "line structure",
      "unity of direction",
      "organisational structure",
      "clarity of objective",
    ],
    answer: "organisational structure",
  },
  {
    question: "Modern means of payment is greatly facilitated by _____",
    options: ["e-banking", "paper money", "credit transfer", "e-commerce"],
    answer: "e-banking",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A country is said to be experiencing an unfavourable balance of trade if her _____",
    options: [
      "exports exceed imports",
      "visible imports exceed visible exports",
      "visible exports exceed visible imports",
      "imports and exports are equal",
    ],
    answer: "visible imports exceed visible exports",
  },
  {
    question:
      "An undertaking given by a person to another assuring his integrity is _____",
    options: [
      "proximate cause",
      "insurable interest",
      "fidelity guarantee",
      "subrogation",
    ],
    answer: "fidelity guarantee",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The principle of management that emphasizes the number of subordinates under the direct supervision of a manager is ____",
    options: [
      "unity of command",
      "scalar chain",
      "unity of direction",
      "span of control",
    ],
    answer: "span of control",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Mr. Taju entered into a contract to let a car to Mr. Funbi for his wedding for two days. However, the car had an accident before the first day. Mr. Funbi attempted to claim damages but failed. This implies that the contract was terminated by _____",
    options: ["bankruptcy", "breach", "lapse of time", "frustration"],
    answer: "frustration",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The agency that currently oversees the privatization and commercialization processes in Nigeria is the _____",
    options: [
      "Nigerian Stock Exchange",
      "Technical Committee on Privatization and Commercialization",
      "Securities and Exchange Commission",
      "Bureau of Public Enterprises",
    ],
    answer: "Bureau of Public Enterprises",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A doctor who attends to patients at home after his official duty is _____",
    options: [
      "a direct and indirect labour",
      "directly employed",
      "self-employed",
      "an employee",
    ],
    answer: "self-employed",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A corporation that is engaged in both primary and secondary activities is referred to as a _____",
    options: ["manufacturer", "trader", "conglomerate", "retailer"],
    answer: "conglomerate",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The use of a personal computer to store data and files that can be accessed by other computers on a network is called _____",
    options: ["memory", "sharing", "networking", "spooling"],
    answer: "networking",
  },
  {
    question: "The primary purpose of commercial banks is to _____",
    options: [
      "encourage savings",
      "give loans",
      "promote insurance",
      "collect bills",
    ],
    answer: "give loans",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Financial resources available to an organisation at any given time can best be referred to as _____",
    options: ["liabilities", "working capital", "assets", "equity"],
    answer: "working capital",
  },
  {
    question: "One of the major limitations of large-scale production is _____",
    options: [
      "specialization",
      "high costs",
      "division of labour",
      "low prices",
    ],
    answer: "high costs",
  },
  {
    question: "The three main economic sectors are _____",
    options: [
      "agriculture, manufacturing, and service",
      "transportation, finance, and insurance",
      "industry, trade, and agriculture",
      "construction, transport, and manufacturing",
    ],
    answer: "agriculture, manufacturing, and service",
  },
  {
    question: "The first step in the marketing research process is to _____",
    options: [
      "analyze data",
      "define the research problem",
      "determine the research objectives",
      "develop the research design",
    ],
    answer: "define the research problem",
  },
];
